<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The blessed publicane Briefly shewing foorth the happy estate of humble repentant sinners. Written by John Orphinstraunge.</title>
            <author>Orphinstraunge, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1625-1630</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 15 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08535</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18854</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103532</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839284</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839284</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3690</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08535)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3690)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 716:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The blessed publicane Briefly shewing foorth the happy estate of humble repentant sinners. Written by John Orphinstraunge.</title>
                  <author>Orphinstraunge, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By T. C[otes] for Iohn Orphinstraunge,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[ca. 1625-1630?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Publication date conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ B² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3690:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 29 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:3690:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 29 -->
            <p>THE BLESSED PVBLICANE.</p>
            <p>Briefly ſhewing foorth the happy eſtate of humble repentant Sinners.</p>
            <p>Written by John Orphinſtraunge.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>PRV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIA</head>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Imprinted at <hi>London</hi> by <hi>T.C.</hi> For <hi>Iohn Orphinſtraunge.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:3690:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 30 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:3690:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 30 -->
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NORABLE, SIR IVLIVS CAESAR, One of his M<hi rend="sup">ties</hi> moſt Honorable Priuie Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell: Together with the Right Worſhipfull, the Doctors of the Ciuill Lawes, and the Maſters of the <hi>Honorable Court of Chancerie.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable, &amp;c.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T may be eſteemed folly in me, if I ſhould ouer-boldly preſſe into your Honors ſtudies with a few lowly Inuocations, or the ſafe Rule to Coeleſtiall Repentance, which is the onely ſcope of this ſmall Treatiſe, if I had not ſome likelihood of your fauourable and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy acceptance; two reaſons inciting me here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto; Firſt, for that it is compacted and faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned together by the Author, who before he knew the world, yea, before, was depriued by death of a great Loſſe, being made fatherles, of ſuch a Father whoſe power was eminent in the Ciuill Lawes and Courts of Chancerie:
<pb facs="tcp:3690:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 31 -->before his child-birth, by the which loſſe, who knoweth not the miſeries that ſuch occaſions inuite miſerable people vnto: The Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> herein is a perfit forme for ſuch as true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repent, in the 37. <hi>Pſalme,</hi> the 25. <hi>verſe,</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>J haue beene young and now am old: and yet ſaw I neuer the righteous forſaken, nor his ſeed beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging their bread:</hi> The other reaſon, is, becauſe whoſoeuer he be, that doth truery read it, firſt, the efficacie and pith of the words; ſecondly, he paines of the poore Author, in digeſting and framing the ſame; thirdly, the profit and benefit of them whoſe zeale thirſt after eternal felicitie. And thus deſiring your friendly acceptance, of my poore endeuors, I humbly, and in all bounden dutie reſt;</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honors, and Worſhips to <hi>the vttmoſt of his power, I. Orphinstrange.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="tripartite_poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:3690:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 31 -->
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The humble and lowly Inuocation to <hi>GOD</hi> the <hi>FATHER.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Reat God of wiſedom, earth, men, waters framing,</l>
                  <l>Giuer of light, of life, of breath and beeing,</l>
                  <l>Glorious <hi>Iehouah</hi> at whoſe mightie naming,</l>
                  <l>All creatures reſt, thy ſelfe all creatures ſeeing.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Melchizedeks</hi> God, him King of peace annointing,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Noahs</hi> Deliuerer, by thy ſole power appointing,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Lots</hi> bleſſed Sauer from the fyred Citie,</l>
                  <l>God of all mercy, grace trueth, and endeleſſe pitie.</l>
                  <l>Father of <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Familie,</l>
                  <l>Righter of <hi>Iacobs</hi> bound calamitie,</l>
                  <l>Keeper of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> from his brethrens rage,</l>
                  <l>Sauer of <hi>Moſes</hi> in his infant age.</l>
                  <l>Guyder of <hi>Ioſuah</hi> in the promiſed land.</l>
                  <l>Scater of <hi>Dauid</hi> with thy out ſtretch't hand,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Direct thy ſeruant whoſe poore pen aſſayes.</l>
                  <l>To adde one mite to thy e're-laſting prayſe.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:3690:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 32 -->
               <head>An humble and lowly Inuocation to GOD the Sonne.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Onne of the Bleſſed, bleſſed euer-liuing,</l>
                  <l>Sunne-ſhine of Glory, and our good thoughts gracing,</l>
                  <l>Store-houſe of treaſure, righteous, euer-giuing.</l>
                  <l>To vs thy mercie and our ſoules chiefe placing,</l>
                  <l>The Port, the Hauen for all men diſtreſſed,</l>
                  <l>Thou free deliuerer of all poore oppreſſed,</l>
                  <l>Thou Paſchall Lambe, thou Enſigne of the iuſt,</l>
                  <l>Thou Fort of glory thou ſureſt hold of truſt,</l>
                  <l>Thou true Meſsias, ſearcher of all hearts,</l>
                  <l>Thou Giuer, Granter, Gracer of all Arts.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Direct thy ſeruant, whoſe poore pen aſſayes,</l>
                  <l>To adde one mite to thy e'relaſting praiſe.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An humble and lowly Inuocation, to GOD the Holy Ghoſt.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Racious true God-head, and Immortall Spirit,</l>
                  <l>The light of goodneſſe and the path to life,</l>
                  <l>The rich Ieruſalem, true heauenly merit,</l>
                  <l>Hater of Folly, and the ſcourge of ſtrife,</l>
                  <l>Ruler of Sapience, councell of the Wiſe,</l>
                  <l>The bleſsed ſtep whereby our ſoules doe riſe,</l>
                  <l>The glaſſe of knowledge, and the prop of bliſse,</l>
                  <l>All onely glory which all glory is,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Inſpire thy ſeruant, whoſe poore pen aſſayes,</l>
                  <l>To adde one mite to thy e'relaſting praiſe</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:3690:4"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 32 -->
            <head>THE BLESSED <hi>P<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BLICANE.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>S there on Earth ought worthy eſtimation,</l>
               <l>That ſinfull man ſhould couet for to liue?</l>
               <l>Is it an outward ſigne deſerues ſaluation,</l>
               <l>Or he be prais'd which with vain hands doth giue</l>
               <l>Then ſhould the Phariſee haue won the praiſe,</l>
               <l>And beene a Light vnto our rich-mens dayes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Hee humbly kneel'd, and did deuoutly pray,</l>
               <l>Whom our ſweet <hi>Sauiour</hi> ſo much eſteem'd,</l>
               <l>He gain'd the Glory of that Sun-ſhine day,</l>
               <l>That prai'd the leſt, yet was the moſt redeem'd,</l>
               <l>He won the bayes, him Chriſt did iuſtifie,</l>
               <l>That growning beg'd in his extremitie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Downe is he couch't within that Sacred bower,</l>
               <l>Where Chriſt our Sauiour ſees his poore diſtreſſe,</l>
               <l>His contrite heart giues not his head the power,</l>
               <l>To looke to heauen, from whence comes all redreſſe,</l>
               <l>His hands are vp, and <hi>[LORD]</hi> he firſt begins,</l>
               <l>To knocke his breſt, for his o're-ſwelling ſinnes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:3690:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 33 -->
               <l>A Sea of teares from foorth his eyes proceed,</l>
               <l>And inwardly his heart to heauen aſcendeth</l>
               <l>His grieued ſoule doth on Ambroſia feed,</l>
               <l>And euer faint the Publican deſcended,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>[Be mercifull]</hi> he cries, O wonders merrour!</l>
               <l>That cryes for mercie being clogd with terrour.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>[BE]</hi> is the next this wreched ſinner ſpeaketh,</l>
               <l>Which word doth ſhew a perfit confidence,</l>
               <l>He is eſpi'd of him he weeping ſeeketh,</l>
               <l>Who cheers his heart and pardons his offence,</l>
               <l>And notes the manner of his humble kneeling,</l>
               <l>Adding more courage to his Chriſtian feeling.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Forward he goeth vnto mercies Seat,</l>
               <l>Arm'd with the reſolution of his heart</l>
               <l>Seeking for mercy though his ſines be great</l>
               <l>To mitigate the rigour of his ſmart,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>[BE MERCIFVLL]</hi> he cryes and pardon me,</l>
               <l>Who humbly begs this mercies gift of thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He calles to minde the follies of his youth,</l>
               <l>His foule tranſgreſſions and his falſe reports,</l>
               <l>His great neglecting of diuineſt Truth,</l>
               <l>Not reading that which vnto good exhorts,</l>
               <l>His gluttony his ſinne yclyped ſhame,</l>
               <l>His vile oppreſſion, loſſe of Chriſtian fame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He thinkes vpon his drunken exerciſe,</l>
               <l>His periur'd ſwearing and his hatefull pride:</l>
               <l>Theſe fond miſdoings come before his eyes,</l>
               <l>Making him begge for mercies ſacred Giude,</l>
               <l>Flying the folly of his former ſinne,</l>
               <l>With humble prayers mercies gift to winne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:3690:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 33 -->
               <l>And as a childe that ſee's the Fathers rod,</l>
               <l>Held vp as inſtance of his Fathers ire;</l>
               <l>Strait cryes for mercie at the hands of God,</l>
               <l>And of his Father pardon doth deſire:</l>
               <l>So this poore wretch, drengh't in a Sea of griefe,</l>
               <l>Humbly begs mercie for his beſt reliefe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Vnto me <hi>LORD, [BE MERCIFVLL,]</hi> he cryes,</l>
               <l>That of all men offended haue thee moſt,</l>
               <l>Receiue thy ſeruant and doe not deſpiſe</l>
               <l>Me wretched creature Sea-wrack't on thy Coaſt:</l>
               <l>Mercie great <hi>LORD,</hi> in ſuch extremes are ſweet,</l>
               <l>As ayds poore ſoules in a diſtreſſed fleet.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For had I not too much offended thee,</l>
               <l>My true contrition would not vrge me ſo,</l>
               <l>Nor could my ſtubborn heart contented be,</l>
               <l>Thus humbly for thy mercyes gift to goe:</l>
               <l>But God of mercie thou haſt me transformed.</l>
               <l>And with thy mercy let me be adorned.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>[TO ME A SINNER]</hi> that's my hainous cryme,</l>
               <l>A wr<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tched man in miſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rable plight;</l>
               <l>Continuing ſo all my vncertaine time,</l>
               <l>Shuning cl<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y, ſtill walking in darke night:</l>
               <l>Faſt lock't in bondage and in Sathans chaine,</l>
               <l>Till thy ſweet mercie ſet me free againe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Long haue I <hi>SINNER</hi> runne a deſperate courſe,</l>
               <l>In which my folly wounded my poore ſoule</l>
               <l>Like to a miſchiefe euer worſe and worſe</l>
               <l>Which ſpreads farre greater ſeeming mooſtrous foule,</l>
               <l>And I foule monſter now doe humbly pray,</l>
               <l>Thy mercyes gift to waſh my ſinnes away.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:3690:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 34 -->
               <l>So ſhall my ſubſtance being chang'd anew,</l>
               <l>Euer giue thankes to thy e'r-laſting Fame:</l>
               <l>To thee, O <hi>LORD,</hi> to thee belongs the due,</l>
               <l>Prais'd, Bleſt and honoured, be thy glorious Name:</l>
               <l>Let all the earth adorne thy Maieſtie</l>
               <l>That feeds all fleſh, the earth, the Sea, the Skie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus with true confidence he haſteth hence,</l>
               <l>Fully p<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rſwaded that he is forgiuen,</l>
               <l>A<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> b<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eing purg'd from all his vile offence,</l>
               <l>Endeuours ſtill to ſerue thee Euer-liuing.</l>
               <l>And <hi>Iſraels</hi> God doth arme his heart with ioy,</l>
               <l>Which (but er'e-while) was chok'd with ſins annoy.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Being departed; now our bleſſed Light<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>All-<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eeing, Euer-liuing, Sonne of Bliſſe,</l>
               <l>Notes th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> behauiour of this humbl<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d wight,</l>
               <l>Whoſe contrite prayer well accounted is,</l>
               <l>He takes his offring, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd accepts his teares,</l>
               <l>Freely forgiues the folly of his yeeres.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He addes vnto this poore mans commendation,</l>
               <l>An euerlaſting ſtile of dignitie,</l>
               <l>A ſetled ſtate, a ſtate of preſeruation,</l>
               <l>The Scepter, Crow<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, and Mace of Royaltie,</l>
               <l>He makes him Chriſtall, Glorious, pure within;</l>
               <l>Giues him rich clothing, free's his ſoule from ſinne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And hauing thus with odours him annoynted,</l>
               <l>Framing a Garland of the pureſt Bayes,</l>
               <l>Thouſands of Angels attend<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nts he appointed,</l>
               <l>To gard this creature in all righteous wayes,</l>
               <l>That if by chance his foote ſhould ſtep awry,</l>
               <l>They ſtill might ſhield him from iniquitie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:3690:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 34 -->
               <l>And taking glory ſtill in this perfection,</l>
               <l>He euer circles him within his armes,</l>
               <l>Giuing him ſuch a bleſſed ſafe protection,</l>
               <l>As ſure defends him from all enuious harmes,</l>
               <l>Making his foes agaſt that now behold him,</l>
               <l>Which but e're-while with hatefull words controld him</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This true Meſsins, and this wonders framing,</l>
               <l>This Way, this Life, this Pearle of Paradiſe,</l>
               <l>This heauenly Vine, this Word paſt words of naming,</l>
               <l>Did not this begger, nor this wretch deſpiſe:</l>
               <l>But iuſtify'd him. O moſt happy man,</l>
               <l>Being thus Bleſſed, though a <hi>Publican!</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If he, ſole Heauenly, earth's great Arch-protector,</l>
               <l>Thee view'd, thee prais'd, thee rai'd with admiration,</l>
               <l>True Iudge of hearts, hearts righteſt true Director,</l>
               <l>The Sap, the Marrow, Life of our Creation,</l>
               <l>The Faithfull Shepherd, and true Husband-man,</l>
               <l>Reiecting riches, bleſt the <hi>Publican.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Not onely bleſt him, but he ſets him foorth</l>
               <l>As a pure Light vnto the worlds beholding,</l>
               <l>Willing all Chriſtians to behold the Worth</l>
               <l>Of this rich Truth, and his rich Truth's infolding.</l>
               <l>And with an humble heart he wils vs kneele,</l>
               <l>If er'e we wiſh his mercies gift to feele.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Tis not too late to call vnto the Lord,</l>
               <l>If wee ore-ſlip the mornings Sunny rayes.</l>
               <l>Tis not too late to read his holy Word,</l>
               <l>Though wee in folly ſpend our younger dayes,</l>
               <l>If we with ſorrow ſtrike our hardened breſt,</l>
               <l>Our ſinnefull ſoules ſhall with theſe gifts be bleſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:3690:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 35 -->
               <l>What time ſoeuer, ſaith our greateſt God,</l>
               <l>A <hi>Publicane</hi> ſhall turne his wicked wayes,</l>
               <l>I will lay by my heauie yron rod,</l>
               <l>And teach his heart my euerlaſting prayſe,</l>
               <l>And lead his ſteps into the Bleſſed Land,</l>
               <l>Where as a Sarre of Life, he e're ſhall ſtand.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Sure is that place where is no dread nor doubt,</l>
               <l>Sound is that Hope which doth on thee relie.</l>
               <l>Safe is that Fort, where danger is kept out,</l>
               <l>And bleſt are ſuch, whom thou do'ſt iuſtifie,</l>
               <l>Happy, thrice happy is that wretched weight,</l>
               <l>Whom thou protecteſt by thy glorious might.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When ſinfull man doth fall in Sathans ſnare,</l>
               <l>And being falne lyes groueling in the myre,</l>
               <l>Then doth the Feind vrge him to deepe diſpaire,</l>
               <l>Till thy ſweer mercie grant Coeleſtiall fire.</l>
               <l>Which doth refine and cleanſe the droſſie part,</l>
               <l>Framing a new, perfit, and contrite heart.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And though our ſinnes be more then we can beare,</l>
               <l>Yet let vs creepe vnto thy mercie-Seate</l>
               <l>With true contrition let vs neuer feare</l>
               <l>Thy mercies fauor though our ſinnes be great:</l>
               <l>For our miſdoings more thy mercies grace,</l>
               <l>Sith thy great mercies prooues the ſurer place.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Is then thy mercie, and All-ſauing grace,</l>
               <l>The onely thing thy ſeruants doe requeſt,</l>
               <l>Is the beholding of thy glorious face,</l>
               <l>A certaine ſigne our ſilly ſoules are bleſt:</l>
               <l>Then, mightie Lord, on vs thy mercie ſhowre,</l>
               <l>So ſhall we praiſe thy euerlaſting Power.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:3690:7"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 35 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
